CHAPTER 001
If I could see Mayoi Hachikuji
one more time, I wouldn't mind dying.
寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples, 一度[いちど, ひとたび]:once|temporarily|one degree, 会[え]:gathering (esp. Buddhist, festive, etc.), 会[かい]:meeting/assembly|association
八九寺真宵にもう一度会えるなら死んでもいい
For a while, I truly thought that.
一時[ひととき, いっとき]:moment|former times|two-hour period, 一時[いちじ]:one o'clock|once|for a time|, 本気[ほんき]:seriousness/earnestness/truth
僕は一時 本気で思っていた
As for why I didn't do so...
ならばどうしてそうしなかったのかと言えば
Much though I was okay with dying,
perhaps more so,
同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, あるいは:or/possibly
死んでもいいと思うのと同じか
あるいは
I still wanted to live, contrary to expectations.
以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||, 割合[わりあい]:rate|comparatively|contrary to expectations, 生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||
それ以上の割合で 僕は生きていたいと
I felt there was something
for me to do while I'm alive.
生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||, ことがある:(something) has occurred/to have done (something)|(something) happens on occasions, ことになる:it has been decided (so) that/it has been arranged (so) that|it is the result (of)
僕には生きてなすべきことがあると
思っていたからということになるのだろう
When there's family or a lover,
家族[かぞく]:family/members of a family, 恋人[こいびと]:lover/sweetheart
それは家族や恋人
benefactors or friends,
those are factors to consider.
恩人[おんじん]:benefactor/patron, 友人[ゆうじん]:friend, 存在[そんざい]:existence/being, 前提[ぜんてい]:preamble/premise/reason, 気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|
恩人や友人の存在が前提となる気持ちであり
However, humans, or at least I,
少ない[すくない]:few/a little/scarce
しかし 人間は 少なくとも僕は
aren't creatures with such strong self-control
that one would die for an emotion.
気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|, 自律[じりつ]:autonomy (philosophy)|self-control, 生き物[いきもの]:living thing/animal
ただひとつの気持ちだけに殉(じゅん)じられるほどに
自律心の強い生き物ではない
I don't need friends.
友達[ともだち]:friend/companion, 作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||
友達は作らない
Because my strength as a human decreases.
強度[きょうど]:strength/intensity, 下がる[さがる]:to come down|to hang|to move back||
人間強度が下がるから
Those pet phrases became nostalgic,
so weak I've become.
口癖[くちぐせ]:way of saying/favorite phrase/favourite phrase, 懐かしい[なつかしい]:dear/desired/missed, 思い出す[おもいだす]:to recall/to remember/to recollect, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, 弱い[よわい]:weak/frail/delicate
そんな口癖(くちぐせ)を懐(なつ)かしく思い出すくらい
今の僕は弱い
I am weak as a human.
弱い[よわい]:weak/frail/delicate
人間として弱い
Weak, so weak...
弱々しい[よわよわしい]:frail/slender/feminine
弱々しくて弱々しくて
What's weakest of all is that
I don't particularly loathe my weakened self.
弱い[よわい]:weak/frail/delicate, 弱々しい[よわよわしい]:frail/slender/feminine, 決して[けっして, けして]:never/by no means/not in the least, 嫌い[きらい]:dislike|suspicion|distinction, 嫌い[ぎらい]:dislike/hatred/fear
何より弱いと思うのは そんな弱々しくなった自分のことを
決して僕は 嫌いじゃあないからだ
I hold no grudge against it.
憎からず思っているからだ
However, there may be people out there
who cannot forgive me for becoming weaker.
弱い[よわい]:weak/frail/delicate, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.), 許す[ゆるす]:to permit|to exempt (from fine)|to confide in|
だけれどそんな 弱くなってしまった僕を許せない人もいるだろう
Overcoming the hell from spring break,
I still continued to live,
春休み[はるやすみ]:spring break/spring vacation, 地獄[じごく]:hell, 経る[へる]:to pass|to pass through|to experience, 生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||, 続ける[つづける]:to continue/to keep up/to keep on
春休みの地獄を経(へ)て それでも生き続ける僕を
and I'm not one who can't notice
someone glaring at me, wishing for me to die.
見つめる[みつめる]:to stare at/to gaze at/to look hard at, 視線[しせん]:one's line of sight/one's gaze/one's eyes (looking), 気付く[きづく]:to notice/to recognize/to recognise
死ねばいいのにと見つめる視線に 気付かない僕ではない
You really are a fool, Araragi-senpai.
まったく:really/truly|indeed, 愚か[おろか]:foolish/stupid, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
まったく 愚かですねえ 阿良々木先輩
Yeah, it's true.
まったく:really/truly|indeed
ああ まったく
"He that is born a fool
is never cured until death."
馬鹿[ばか, バカ]:fool|trivial matter|foolish|, 治る[なおる]:to be cured/to get well|to get mended
馬鹿は死ななきゃ治らない
On the other hand,
if it's something that death will cure,
逆[ぎゃく]:reverse|converse (of a hypothesis, etc.)|inverse (function), 逆[さか]:inverse/reverse, 治る[なおる]:to be cured/to get well|to get mended, 程度[ていど]:degree/amount/grade
逆に言うなら 死んで治る程度のものなら
KOYOMI ARARAGI
being a fool may not have been
that terrible of an illness, either.
馬鹿[ばか, バカ]:fool|trivial matter|foolish|, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing, 病気[びょうき]:illness/disease/sickness, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
馬鹿もそんなに 悪い病気じゃあないのかもしれなかった
MAYOI HELL - PART ONE
CHAPTER 002
H-Hachikuji?
はちく:breaking bamboo, はちく:Henon bamboo (Phyllostachys nigra var. henonis)
は... はちくじ?
Yes.
はい
Hachikuji?
寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples
八九寺?
Yes, that's right.
はい そうです
Mayoi Hachikuji?
寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples
八九寺真宵?
Yes, I'm Mayoi Hachikuji.
寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples
はい 八九寺真宵です
Now wait, hold on.
いや 待て待て
Don't panic.
慌てる[あわてる]:to become confused (disconcerted, disorganized, disorganised)/to be flustered|to be in a hurry
慌(あわ)てるな
ARARAGI
KOYOMI
Right, just remember...
思い出す[おもいだす]:to recall/to remember/to recollect
そうだ 思い出せ
What kind of a situation was this now?
一体[いったい]:...the heck (e.g. "what the heck?")|one object|one form||, どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.), シチュエーション:situation
今は一体 どんなシチュエーションなのだっけ?
Exam-taker number: 0049
Name: Araragi, Koyomi
Foreign Subjects Taken:
English, German, Chinese, Russian, Japanese
(circle two subjects that apply)
Right. Today, March 13th
was the day of my entrance exams.
三[さん, み]:three|tri-, 三[サン]:three, 受験[じゅけん]:taking an examination (esp. school and university entrance)
そう 今日 三月十三日は 受験日だった
Exam Date: 3/13/xxxx (Tue)
General Entrance Exams
Japanese - oo:oo ~ oo:oo
Before heading to the college campus
to take the exam, I had made a detour.
構内[こうない]:premises/grounds/campus, 試験を受ける[しけんをうける]:to sit for an examination, 向かう[むかう]:to face|to go towards/to head towards, 寄り道[よりみち]:dropping in on the way/breaking one's journey/making a stopover
僕は大学の構内へと 試験を受けに向かう前に
寄り道をしたのだった
There, I saw the leader of the specialists,
神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 境内[けいだい]:grounds (esp. of shrines and temples)/compound/churchyard
そこで 僕は神社の境内(けいだい)で僕を待つ
Gaen Izuko-san, waiting for me within
the shrine grounds, and I had to face her.
専門家[せんもんか]:specialist/expert/professional, 総領[そうりょう]:eldest child|child who carries on the family name|pre-ritsuryo official established in key provinces, responsible for administration of his home and surrounding provinces|, 総領[すべおさ]:pre-ritsuryo official established in key provinces, responsible for administration of his home and surrounding provinces, 湖[みずうみ]:lake, 湖[こ]:lake (in place names), 向き合う[むきあう]:to be opposite/to face each other, ことになる:it has been decided (so) that/it has been arranged (so) that|it is the result (of)
専門家の総領 臥煙(がえん)伊豆湖(いずこ)さんと向き合うことになって
And?
And, why Hachikuji?
寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples
で どうして八九寺?
Mayoi Hachikuji-san?
寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples
八九寺真宵さん?
Oh, brother.
Looks like there's a problem.
困る[こまる]:to be troubled/to be worried/to be bothered, ことになる:it has been decided (so) that/it has been arranged (so) that|it is the result (of)
やれやれ 困ったことになっちまったぜ
From this turn of events,
展開[てんかい]:development|expansion|expansion
この展開からすると
I'm sure everyone is thinking of
a surprising reunion with someone
どうせ:anyhow/in any case|at best, 暦[こよみ, れき]:calendar/almanac, 二[に, ふた]:two, 二[アル]:two, 度[たび, たんび]:time (three times, each time, etc.)/times, 度[ど]:degree (angle, temperature, scale, etc.)|counter for occurrences and times|strength (of alcohol), 会[え]:gathering (esp. Buddhist, festive, etc.), 会[かい]:meeting/assembly|association, 相手[あいて]:companion|other party|opponent (sports, etc.)
どうせみんな 阿良々木暦はもう二度と会えないと思っていた相手
Koyomi Araragi would never see again,
the one close to his heart, Mayoi Hachikuji,
意中[いちゅう]:one's mind/one's heart/one's intention, 寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples, 思い[おもい]:thought|imagination|desire||, 再会[さいかい]:another meeting/meeting again/reunion, ことができる:can (do)/to be able to (do)/can be done
意中の八九寺真宵に思いもよらぬ再会をすることができて
jumping for joy, choked with gratified tears,
trembling from the touching moment,
欣喜[きんき]:pleasure, 雀躍[じゃくやく]:leaping for joy/exultation, 感涙[かんるい]:tears of gratitude, 咽び泣く[むせびなく]:to sob/to be choked with tears, 感動[かんどう]:being deeply moved emotionally/excitement/passion, 打ち震える[うちふるえる]:to tremble
欣喜雀躍(きんきじゃくやく) 感涙(かんるい)に咽(むせ)び泣き
感動に打ち震え
rejoicing and screaming nonsense,
and he would first attempt to hug her.
ながら:while/during|while, 喜び勇む[よろこびいさむ]:to be in high spirits, ともあれ:anyhow/in any case, しにかかる:to be dying
わけのわからないことを言いながら 喜び勇んで
何はともあれ まずは彼女にハグしにかかると
I'm sure that's what everyone expects.
期待[きたい]:expectation/anticipation/hope
期待しちゃってるんだろうな
I'm sure that's what is expected of me.
期待[きたい]:expectation/anticipation/hope
期待されちゃってるんだろうな 僕
That's quite the burden of expectation.
ほとほと:quite (usu. negative connotation)/utterly/really, 重い[おもい]:heavy|heavy (feeling)|slow||, 期待[きたい]:expectation/anticipation/hope
ほとほと重い期待だよ
My adolescent self, the one who
jumped at Hachikuji with a rocket-like start
町[まち, ちょう]:town|street|109.09 m||, 歩く[あるく]:to walk, 寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples, 見かける[みかける]:to (happen to) see/to notice/to catch sight of, ロケット:rocket, スタート:start, 飛びつく[とびつく]:to jump at/to be attracted by, 頃[ころ, ごろ]:(approximate) time|suitable time (or condition)|time of year, 頃[けい]:qing (Chinese unit of land area equal to 100 mu)
町を歩き 八九寺を見かけては
ロケットスタートで飛びついていたあの頃の
each time he saw her walking around town,
is no longer here.
あどけない:innocent/cherubic
あどけなき僕はもういないのだ
If that is Koyomi Araragi, then he is already dead.
暦[こよみ, れき]:calendar/almanac
それが阿良々木暦だとすれば 彼はもう死んだのだ
He. Is. Dead.
デッド:dead
彼・イズ・デッドだ
Such a Koyomi Araragi
that is better off dead, really was dead.
暦[こよみ, れき]:calendar/almanac
そんな死んだほうがいいような阿良々木暦は
本当に死んだのである
He met a fitting end.
ふさわしい:appropriate/adequate/suitable, 死[し]:death|death penalty (by strangulation or decapitation)|(an) out, 迎える[むかえる]:to go out to meet|to receive|to accept (e.g. as a member of a group or family)||
ふさわしき死を迎えた
But well, that said...
でもまあねえ そうは言っても
That said...
そうは言ってもだ
Tracing back the faint threads of memory,
I am indebted to Hachikuji quite a bit as well.
かすか:faint/dim|poor, 記憶[きおく]:memory/recollection|storage, 糸[いと]:thread/yarn/string, 糸[し]:thread|0.001/one ten-thousandth, 辿る[たどる]:to follow (road)/to pursue (course)/to follow up, 限り[かぎり]:limit|degree|as far as possible||, 限り[きり]:end|bounds|delivery date (of a futures contract)||, 寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples, 随分[ずいぶん]:very/extremely|contemptible, 世話になる[せわになる]:to receive favor (favour)/to be much obliged to someone/to be indebted
かすかな記憶の糸を辿(たど)ってみる限り
僕も八九寺には随分と世話になったものじゃあないか
Benevolence, justice, rites, knowledge,
loyalty, integrity, filial piety, sibling piety.
仁義[じんぎ]:humanity and justice (esp. in Confucianism)|duty|formal greeting (between gamblers)|, 忠信[ちゅうしん]:faithfulness/devotion, 孝悌[こうてい]:filial piety/brotherly love
仁義礼智忠信孝悌(じんぎれいちちゅうしんこうてい)
BENEVOLENCE, JUSTICE, RITES,
KNOWLEDGE, LOYALTY, INTEGRITY,
FILIAL PIETY, SIBLING PIETY
Return gratitude worth returning.
返す[かえす]:to return (something)|to turn over|to pay back|, 恩[おん]:favour/favor/obligation
返すべき恩は返すべきだし
It is only natural to approach someone
who took care of you with gratitude.
世話になる[せわになる]:to receive favor (favour)/to be much obliged to someone/to be indebted, 相手[あいて]:companion|other party|opponent (sports, etc.), 礼[れい]:thanks|manners|bow||, 接する[せっする]:to touch|to receive (e.g. visitor)|to receive (news)||, 当たり前[あたりまえ]:natural/reasonable|usual
世話になった相手に
礼をもって接するのは当たり前のことである
If that's been decided, then all is well.
決まる[きまる]:to be decided/to be settled|to look good in (clothes), 弥栄[いやさか, やさか]:prosperity/prospering|best of luck
そうと決まれば弥栄(いやさか)弥栄
On your mark, get set...
位置につく[いちにつく]:to take one's place/to take one's position/to go into position, 用意[ようい]:preparation/arrangements/provision
位置について はーあ 用意
Hachikuji!
寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples
八九寺!
Hachikuji! Hachikuji! Hachikuji!
寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples
八九寺ー! 八九寺ー! 八九寺ー!
What are you doing here?
Why are you here for me right now?
お前なんでここにいるんだよ
どうしてここにいてくれちゃってるんだよ!?
No, I don't care about the reason,
I'm just happy that you're here for me.
理由[りゆう, わけ]:reason/pretext/motive, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
いや理由なんてどうでもいい
お前がここにいてくれるだけでいい
I can't put these touching feelings to words!
感動[かんどう]:being deeply moved emotionally/excitement/passion, 言葉[ことば, けとば]:language|word|speech
この感動 言葉にならねえ
Oh, how this feels to the touch...
The feeling of huggin you...
手触り[てざわり]:feel/touch, 心地[ここち]:feeling/sensation|sensation of doing (usu. after -masu stem of verb), 心地[しんじ]:padding/lining/foundation
ああこの手触り 抱き心地
This size, and how it
completely fits within my arms!
腕[うで]:arm|skill/efforts, 腕[かいな]:arm (esp. upper arm)|counter used to measure the thickness of round objects, すっぽり:entirely/completely|cleanly, 収まる[おさまる]:to be in one's place|to be delivered|to be settled||, サイズ:size, 感[かん]:feeling/sensation|interjection
僕の腕の中にすっぽり収まるサイズ感
This truly is Hachikuji!
まさしく:surely/no doubt/evidently, 寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples
まさしく八九寺だー!
Thankful, so thankful!
ありがたやありがたや!
The more we rub cheeks,
the more it feels like Hachikuji!
頬[ほお, ほほ]:cheek (of face), 頬[つら]:face|surface|surrounding area|, 擦る[こする]:to rub/to scrub, 擦る[さする]:to pat|to rub off|to be equal to|, 寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples
頬擦(ほおず)れば頬擦るほどに八九寺だ!
The more I lick around,
the more it feels like Hachikuji!
舐める[なめる]:to lick|to taste|to experience (esp. a hardship)|, まわす[まわす]:to turn|to circulate|to surround||, 寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples
舐(な)めまわせば舐めまわすほど八九寺だ!
The more it ripens,
the more I can lick Hachikuji!
実る[みのる]:to bear fruit/to ripen, 頭[とう]:counter for large animals (e.g. head of cattle), 頭[あたま, かしら]:head|hair (on one's head)|mind||, 舐める[なめる]:to lick|to taste|to experience (esp. a hardship)|, 寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples
実るほど頭(こうべ)を舐める八九寺かな!
Come on, let me touch you more!
もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, 触る[さわる]:to touch/to feel
ええい もっと触らせろ
Let me hug you more!
もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, 抱きつく[だきつく]:to cling to/to embrace
もっと抱きつかせろ
Let me lick you more!
もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, 舐める[なめる]:to lick|to taste|to experience (esp. a hardship)|, させる:to make (someone) do|to allow (someone) to, させる:(usu. followed by a negative form) worth special consideration
もっと舐めさせろー!
Hey now! Don't thrash about!
It's harder for us to get naked!
暴れる[あばれる]:to act violently/to rage/to struggle, 互い[たがい]:mutual/reciprocal, 裸になる[はだかになる]:to take off one's clothes/to undress, づらい:difficult to .../hard to ...
こら! 暴れるな!
お互い裸(はだか)になりづらいだろうが!
Ow, ow, ow, ow, ow!
What the hell are you doing, brat?
痛い[いたい]:painful/sore|exceeding, 痛い[いたい]:painful/sore|exceeding
痛い痛い痛い痛い痛い! 何すんだこのガキ!
CHAPTER 003
How to put it...
なんっかさあ...
That's right. After I parted ways with you,
別れる[わかれる]:to part (usu. of people)|to separate (of a couple)|to lose (e.g. one's mother), 後[あと]:behind|after|after one's death||, 後[のち]:later|future|after one's death|
そうだよ お前と別れた後
SEISHIROU SHISHIRUI
Shinobu's first minion showed up,
一人[ひとり, いちにん]:one person|alone/unmarried, 目[め]:eye|eyesight|look||, 眷属[けんぞく]:(one's) family/dependents|follower, 現れる[あらわれる]:to appear/to come in sight|to be expressed (e.g. emotions)
忍の一人目の眷属(けんぞく)が現れたり
Oikura returned,
老[ろう]:old age/age/old people, 倉[くら]:warehouse/storehouse/cellar, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
老倉が戻ってきたり
SODACHI OIKURA
Sengoku had all that happen
to her here at this shrine,
神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, あんな:such (about something or someone distant from both speaker and listener, or about a situation unfamiliar to both speaker and listener)/so/that, あんな:Anna or Anwa era (968.8.13-970.3.25), ことになる:it has been decided (so) that/it has been arranged (so) that|it is the result (of)
千石がこの神社であんなことになったり
NADEKO SENGOKU
DEISHU KAIKI
I bumped into Kaiki,
貝木(かいき)と会っちまったり
KOYOMI ARARAGI
I turned into a vampire on my own,
独自[どくじ]:original/unique|independent, 吸血鬼[きゅうけつき]:vampire/bloodsucker, 化[か]:action of making something/-ification
僕が独自に吸血鬼化しちまったり
that and I had Ononoki-chan
kill one of her own creators,
斧[おの]:axe/hatchet, 乃[の]:possessive particle, 木[き]:tree/shrub|wood, 木[もく]:Thursday|wood (first of the five elements), 生みの親[うみのおや]:biological parent|founder/creator, 一人[ひとり, いちにん]:one person|alone/unmarried
それに 斧乃木(おののき)ちゃんに生みの親の一人を殺させちまったり
YOTSUGI ONONOKI
SURUGA KANBARU
oh right, that was here at this shrine, too.
神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine
ああ それもこの神社でのことだったか
KAREN ARARAGI / TSUKIHI ARARAGI
YODURU KAGENUI
And also at this shrine,
Kagenui-san went missing, too.
やっぱり:too/also|still, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 影[かげ]:shadow|reflection|ominous sign||, 行方不明[ゆくえふめい]:missing/unaccounted for
そしてやっぱりこの神社で
影縫(かげぬい)さんが行方不明になったりな
I had one bad thing
happen to me after another.
立て続け[たてつづけ]:succession/continuation/series, 酷い[むごい]:cruel/merciless|tragic, 酷い[ひどい]:cruel|violent|very bad|, ばっかり:only/merely|approximately, 起きる[おきる]:to get up|to wake up|to occur (usu. of unfavourable incidents)
立て続けに 酷いことばっかり起きて
For all this time, I called the two weeks
of spring break as a hellish time for me.
春休み[はるやすみ]:spring break/spring vacation, 二[に, ふた]:two, 二[アル]:two, 週間[しゅうかん]:weeks (period of), ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.), 地獄[じごく]:hell, 表現[ひょうげん]:expression/presentation|representation, してき:historic/historical, してき:pointing out/identification
春休みの二週間のことを
僕はずっと地獄のようだったと表現してきたけれども
But the true hell
may have been the past six months—
真[しん]:truth|seriousness|logical TRUE||, 真[ま]:just|pure|truth, 地獄[じごく]:hell, むしろ:rather/better/instead, むしろ:woven mat (esp. one made of straw)|seat, 半年[はんとし, はんねん]:half year, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
真の地獄はむしろ この半年だったのかもしれないと
That's incorrect, Araragi-san.
違いますよ 阿良々木さん
Hm? What is?
ん... え 何が?
Ara-lucky-san.
ラッキー:lucky
あらラッキーさん
Hachikuji, I was just talking about how
unfortunate of a person I had been.
寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples, 不幸[ふこう]:unhappiness/sorrow|death (usu. of a relative), 話をする[はなしをする]:to have a talk/to tell a story
八九寺 僕は今
どれだけ自分が不幸だったかって話をしていたところなんだ
I don't care how you flub, but just don't flub
in such a positive, happy light like that.
どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.), 噛む[かむ]:to bite|to crash against (e.g. of waves)|to engage (of cogs, zippers, etc.)||, 噛む[しがむ]:to chew (strongly), たって:strongly hoping or requesting (of something that is difficult to be brought to fruition), たって:even if/even though|however, 陽気[ようき]:cheerful|weather|spirit of yang, ハッピー:happy
どんな噛みかたをするにしたって
そんな陽気でハッピーな噛みかただけはしないでくれ
At the least, you should have said Un-lucky-san.
せめて:at least/at most, せめて:offense/offence/method of attack, アンラッキー:unlucky
せめてアンラッキーさんにしてくれ
That, and my name is Araragi.
そして僕の名前は阿良々木だ
I'm sorry. I flubbed.
失礼[しつれい, しつらい]:discourtesy|Excuse me|to leave|, 噛む[かむ]:to bite|to crash against (e.g. of waves)|to engage (of cogs, zippers, etc.)||, 噛む[しがむ]:to chew (strongly)
失礼 噛みました
No, that was intentional.
わざと:on purpose
違う わざとだ
I fwubbed.
噛みまみた
It's not intentional?
わざと:on purpose
わざとじゃない!?
Flub-dub-cub-hub-stub-grub-sub-bub-rub-club-tub.
みなみ:south
噛みまみなみさみなみわみあみやみたみはみらみ
How can you recite that without flubbing?
噛む[かむ]:to bite|to crash against (e.g. of waves)|to engage (of cogs, zippers, etc.)||, 噛む[しがむ]:to chew (strongly), 言える[いえる]:to be possible to say/to be able to say, 台詞[せりふ, かはく]:speech/words/one's lines
よく噛まずに言えるなそんな台詞!
I can't help but marvel at you as you do that!
舌を巻く[したをまく]:to be astonished
そんなお前に僕は舌を巻かずにはいられないよ!
You're incorrect, Araragi-san.
違います 阿良々木さん
It's more realistic an error,
or rather a more practical error...
もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, 現実的[げんじつてき]:realistic/pragmatic, 即物的[そくぶつてき]:practical/matter-of-fact/realistic
もっと現実的に違うというか 即物的に違うというか
To be frank, the location is different.
ありてい:the unvarnished truth, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
ありていに言うと 場所が違うのです
Location?
場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
場所?
For a while, Araragi-san,
先刻[せんこく]:already/a while ago
先刻(せんこく)から阿良々木さん
you've been saying
"this shrine" this, "this shrine" that.
神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 仰る[おっしゃる]:to say/to speak/to tell
"この神社" "この神社"と仰っていますけれども
But, this isn't North Shirahebi Shrine.
北[きた]:north|the North|North Korea|, 北[ペー]:north wind tile|winning hand with a pung (or kong) of north wind tiles, 白蛇[しろへび, はくじゃ]:albino Japanese rat snake, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, ではある:to be (in contrast to something that is not the case)
ここは北白蛇神社ではありませんよ
Huh? What?
え... あれ え?
And, it's not even that park
where I first met you, Araragi-san.
出会う[であう]:to meet (by chance)|to meet (e.g. of rivers, highways, etc.)|to emerge and engage (an enemy), 公園[こうえん]:(public) park
そして 私と阿良々木さんが出会った
あの公園でさえありませんよ
What?
Araragi-san,
please stay calm and listen to me.
落ち着く[おちつく]:to calm down|to calm down|to settle down (in a location, job, etc.)||, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
阿良々木さん 落ち着いて聞いてくださいね
Araragi-san, you may be thinking that I,
成仏[じょうぶつ]:entering Nirvana/becoming a Buddha|going to heaven, わたし:I/me|private affairs, わたし:ferry (crossing)/ferry(boat)|delivery
阿良々木さんは 成仏したはずのわたしが
someone who has rested in peace,
have returned before you.
再び[ふたたび]:again/once more/a second time, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
再び阿良々木さんの前に帰ってきたのだと
思ってらっしゃるのかもしれませんけれど
But actually, in reality, that is not the case.
実[じつ, じち]:truth|sincerity|content|, 実[み]:fruit|seed|(in broth) pieces of meat, vegetable, etc.|, 事実[じじつ]:fact/truth/reality
しかし実は 事実はそうではないのです
What?
なに?
WHAT
It's not that I have appeared
before you, Araragi-san.
わたし:I/me|private affairs, わたし:ferry (crossing)/ferry(boat)|delivery, 現れる[あらわれる]:to appear/to come in sight|to be expressed (e.g. emotions)
わたしが阿良々木さんの前に現れたのではなく
Araragi-san, you were the one
who appeared before me, okay?
わたし:I/me|private affairs, わたし:ferry (crossing)/ferry(boat)|delivery, 現れる[あらわれる]:to appear/to come in sight|to be expressed (e.g. emotions)
阿良々木さんがわたしの前に現れたのですよ?
WHAT
What, what?
WHAT²
Araragi-san, early in the morning on March 13th,
you visited said North Shirahebi Shrine,
三[さん, み]:three|tri-, 三[サン]:three, 早朝[そうちょう]:early morning, 件[くだん]:the aforementioned/the said|the usual, 件[けん]:matter/case/item, 北[きた]:north|the North|North Korea|, 北[ペー]:north wind tile|winning hand with a pung (or kong) of north wind tiles, 白蛇[しろへび, はくじゃ]:albino Japanese rat snake, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 訪れる[おとずれる, おとづれる]:to visit/to call on|to arrive
阿良々木さん あなたは三月十三日の早朝
件(くだん)の北白蛇神社を訪れて
met with Gaen Izuko-san,
and you were murdered.
湖[みずうみ]:lake, 湖[こ]:lake (in place names)
臥煙伊豆湖さんとお会いして
そして殺されたのです
And that solution is for you to die.
解決策[かいけつさく]:solution/solution strategy
その解決策はきみが死ぬことだ
It's all right. It will only hurt for an instant.
痛い[いたい]:painful/sore|exceeding, 一瞬[いっしゅん]:instant/moment/for an instant
大丈夫 痛いのは一瞬だよ
HACHIKUJI BUS
This place, Araragi-san...
ここはですね 阿良々木さん
is Hell.
地獄[じごく]:hell
地獄です
What?
はい?
The bottommost layer of hell
among all hells...
地獄[じごく]:hell, 最[さい]:the most/the extreme|prime, 下層[かそう]:lower strata (classes)
地獄の中でも最下層の地獄
Avici Hell.
阿鼻[あび]:Avici (lowest level of hell), 地獄[じごく]:hell
阿鼻(あび)地獄です
CHAPTER 004
Hell? Hell? Avici Hell?
地獄[じごく]:hell, 阿鼻[あび]:Avici (lowest level of hell)
地獄!? 地獄!? 阿鼻地獄!?
SANJIVA / KALASUTRA / SAMGHATA /
RAURAVA / MAHARAURAVA / TAPANA
Let's say this is indeed Avici.
I have one big question.
阿鼻[あび]:Avici (lowest level of hell), 地獄[じごく]:hell, 大きな[おおきな]:big/large/great, 疑問[ぎもん]:question/problem/doubt
ここが阿鼻地獄だとして 大きな疑問がひとつ
Oh, you're wondering why you fell into
such a deep part of hell, Araragi-san?
深[み]:august|beautiful, 深[ふけ]:growing late/latening, 地獄[じごく]:hell, 落ちる[おちる]:to fall down|to be omitted|to decrease||, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
ああ どうして阿良々木さんが
そこまでの深き地獄に落ちてしまったのかということですね?
You see, Araragi-san,
you have turned into a vampire, right?
HMRGH?
吸血鬼[きゅうけつき]:vampire/bloodsucker, 化[か]:action of making something/-ification, なさる:to do
ほら 阿良々木さんは吸血鬼化なさっているじゃないですか
The main sin that lowered you down
to Avichi is just that. Saving a demon.
阿鼻[あび]:Avici (lowest level of hell), 地獄[じごく]:hell, 落ちる[おちる]:to fall down|to be omitted|to decrease||, 鬼[おに, き]:oni|spirit of a deceased person|ogre-like person (i.e. fierce, relentless, merciless, etc.)||, 助ける[たすける]:to save|to help|to aid|
こうして阿鼻地獄に落ちている主罪はそれですよ 鬼を助けるって
TOUR OF HELL
Of course you'd go to hell for that.
そりゃ:very/extremely|that is, 地獄[じごく]:hell, 行き[ゆき, いき]:bound for ...|going (to)
そりゃ地獄行きですよ
I see.
そうか
No, the big question I had
wasn't about my grave sin.
抱く[いだく, だく]:to embrace|to harbour (e.g. grudge)|to have sex with|, 大きな[おおきな]:big/large/great, 疑問[ぎもん]:question/problem/doubt, 大罪[だいざい, たいざい]:serious crime/grave sin
いや 僕が抱いた大きな疑問というのは
僕の大罪についてではない
What the hell are you doing here?
なんでお前ここにいるんだよ!
Why, you ask...
なんでと言われましても
そりゃあ:very/extremely|that is, わたし:I/me|private affairs, わたし:ferry (crossing)/ferry(boat)|delivery, 地獄[じごく]:hell, 落ちる[おちる]:to fall down|to be omitted|to decrease||
そりゃあほら わたし 地獄に落ちましたから
But well, you see, I fell down to hell.
You've got to be kidding me.
After such a touching resting into peace!?
嘘[うそ, ウソ]:lie|mistake|unwise move|, 感動的[かんどうてき]:moving/touching/stirring, 成仏[じょうぶつ]:entering Nirvana/becoming a Buddha|going to heaven, ながら:while/during|while
嘘(うそ)だろお前
あれだけ感動的に成仏しておきながら
You fell to hell after that?
Seriously? That was such a waste!
後[あと]:behind|after|after one's death||, 後[のち]:later|future|after one's death|, 地獄[じごく]:hell, 落ちる[おちる]:to fall down|to be omitted|to decrease||, 台無し[だいなし]:mess/spoiled/spoilt, じゃん:isn't it
その後地獄に落ちたの!? マジで!? 台無しじゃん!
What are you doing? This just can't be!
何やってんのお前!? ありえないだろ!
See, I didn't know
until I fell down here myself.
わたし:I/me|private affairs, わたし:ferry (crossing)/ferry(boat)|delivery, 落ちる[おちる]:to fall down|to be omitted|to decrease||
ほら わたしも落ちるまで知らなかったんですけれど
When children die before their parents,
they apparently go straight to hell, no matter what.
子供[こども]:child/children, 親[おや]:parent|dealer (in cards, mahjong, etc.)|founder|, 親[しん]:intimacy|close relative|pro- (e.g. pro-American, pro-Japanese, etc.), 先[さき]:previous|point (e.g. pencil)|head (of a line)||, 先[せん]:former/previous|first move (in go, shogi, etc.), 問答[もんどう]:questions and answers/dialogue, 無用[むよう]:useless|unnecessary|not on business|, 地獄[じごく]:hell, 行き[ゆき, いき]:bound for ...|going (to), らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
子供って親よりも先に死ぬと
問答無用で地獄行きらしいんですよ
IT'S THAT BIT ABOUT PILING UP STONES ON THE BANKS OF HELL
You're kidding, right?
嘘[うそ, ウソ]:lie|mistake|unwise move|
嘘だろ おい
Hmm? What's the matter, Araragi-san?
ん? どうしました? 阿良々木さん
But still...
それでも
That's not a sin that would make you fall
all the way down to Avichi unlike me, right?
阿鼻[あび]:Avici (lowest level of hell), 地獄[じごく]:hell, 落ちる[おちる]:to fall down|to be omitted|to decrease||, 罪[つみ]:crime|penalty|fault|
それって 僕と違って
阿鼻地獄にまで落ちる罪ってわけじゃあないだろう?
Shouldn't you be piling stones
on the banks of hell?
賽の河原[さいのかわら]:Children's Limbo|futile/unrewarding, 石積み[いしづみ]:masonry/stonework
賽の河原での石積み だろう?
Yes, that's right, Araragi-san.
ええ そうなんですよ 阿良々木さん
I knew this is where
you'd come falling down to, Araragi-san.
落下[らっか]:fall/drop/coming down, 地点[ちてん]:site/point on a map/spot
ここが阿良々木さんの落下地点であることはわかっていました
That is why I took a trip
from the banks of Hell to pick you up.
わたし:I/me|private affairs, わたし:ferry (crossing)/ferry(boat)|delivery, 河原[かわら]:dry river bed/river beach, 出張[しゅっちょう]:official tour/business trip, してき:historic/historical, してき:pointing out/identification, 出迎える[でむかえる]:to meet/to greet
だからわたしは わたしのいるべき河原から出張してきて
ここにお出迎えに来ていたのですよ
"It looks like I'm having a friend come nearby,
so I'll take a break from piling stones today!"
友達[ともだち]:friend/companion, 近く[ちかく]:near|nearly (e.g. "it took nearly one year")|shortly, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, 石積み[いしづみ]:masonry/stonework, お休み[おやすみ]:holiday|sleep|Good night
なんか友達が近くまで来るみたいなんで
ちょっと今日の石積みお休みしまーす
That's how I got out of there.
感じ[かんじ]:feeling/sense/impression, 抜ける[ぬける]:to come out|to fade|to wear a hole (e.g. clothes)||
って感じで抜けてきました
So the banks of hell
is that easygoing a place to be?
気安い[きやすい]:relaxed/familiar/easy to access, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho, 賽の河原[さいのかわら]:Children's Limbo|futile/unrewarding
そんな気安い場所なのか 賽の河原って!
You had known in advance?
あらかじめ:beforehand/in advance/previously
あらかじめわかっていた?
No, it's not that I knew.
The person who told me about it, did know.
わたし:I/me|private affairs, わたし:ferry (crossing)/ferry(boat)|delivery, 教える[おしえる]:to teach|to tell|to preach
いえ わたしがというより
わたしにそれを教えてくれた人が ですけれど
Apparently that person...
あのかたはなんでも
...knows everything.
何でも知っている そうですから
CHAPTER 005
Now that all the detailed explanations
for every mystery has been explained,
謎[なぞ]:riddle/puzzle|enigmatic, 詳細[しょうさい]:detail/particulars, 解説[かいせつ]:explanation/commentary/exposition, 済む[すむ]:to finish|to merely result in something less severe than expected|to feel at ease|
さて すべての謎についての詳細な解説も済んだことですし
let us start heading over.
そろそろ:slowly/quietly|soon, 向かう[むかう]:to face|to go towards/to head towards
そろそろ向かいましょうか
Let's go, Araragi-san.
行きますよ 阿良々木さん
Hachikuji, you haven't had any hesitation
in your steps at all until here.
寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples, さっき:some time ago/just now, さっき:thirst for blood/bloodlust/determination to kill, 足取り[あしどり]:gait/walk|trace (e.g. of route taken by hunted criminal), 足取り[あしとり]:downing an opponent by grabbing his leg, 迷い[まよい]:hesitation/bewilderment|inability to reach enlightenment
八九寺 さっきから足取りに迷いがないけれど
At the least, can you tell me
where our destination is?
目的地[もくてきち]:place of destination
まずは目的地だけでも聞かせてくれないか?
To tell you the destination where we are heading
based on the objective for heading there...
向かう[むかう]:to face|to go towards/to head towards, 目的地[もくてきち]:place of destination, 目的[もくてき]:purpose/goal/aim
どこに向かっているのかという目的地を
向かっているその目的から言うとですね
Araragi-san, it's my job
to resurrect you back to life.
生き返る[いきかえる]:to revive/to come to oneself/to be restored to life, わたし:I/me|private affairs, わたし:ferry (crossing)/ferry(boat)|delivery, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
阿良々木さんを生き返らせるのがわたしの仕事なのですよ
Eh? I can be resurrected?
生き返る[いきかえる]:to revive/to come to oneself/to be restored to life
え? 僕って生き返れるの?
Of course you can.
What are you going to do by staying dead?
そりゃ:very/extremely|that is
そりゃそうでしょう 死んでどうするんですか
But, Gaen-san...
でも... 臥煙さんが
No, that's why you need
to get a grip, Araragi-san.
しっかり:tightly (holding on)/firmly|strongly (built), くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
いやだから しっかりしてくださいよ 阿良々木さん
In other words,
"dying then resurrecting" was included
生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||, 含める[ふくめる]:to include (in a group or scope)|to instruct|to include (a nuance)||
つまりは "殺して生き返らす" ところまで含めて
in everything proceeding according
to her calculations.
計算[けいさん]:calculation/reckoning|forecast, 通り[とおり]:avenue|coming and going|flow (of water, air, etc.)||, 通り[どおり]:in accordance with|roughly|Street
そのかたの計算通りだったということでしょうが
What's up with that fruitless calculation?
不毛[ふもう]:sterile/barren/unproductive, 計算[けいさん]:calculation/reckoning|forecast
なんだその不毛な計算は
That's a pretty meaningless act, much like
dividing by two after multiplying by two.
掛ける[かける]:to hang (e.g. picture)|to sit|to take (time, money)||, 割る[わる]:to divide|to cut|to break||, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance, 行為[こうい]:act/deed/conduct
２を掛けたあとで２で割るみたいな
何の意味もない行為じゃないか
It's not "dividing by two
after multiplying by two."
掛ける[かける]:to hang (e.g. picture)|to sit|to take (time, money)||, 割る[わる]:to divide|to cut|to break||
"２を掛けたあとで２で割る" じゃあないですよ
There is subtraction as well.
引き算[ひきざん]:subtraction
引き算もされています
Well, I'm sure you'll figure it out eventually.
おいおい:Hey!/Wait a minute!|boohoo, おいおい:gradually/by degrees/little by little
まあそれもおいおいわかりますよ
Oh, Araragi-san.
おや 阿良々木さん
Someone has sunken into the ground over there.
あそこ:there (place physically distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|genitals, へたり込む[へたりこむ]:to sit down hard/to sink down to the floor
あそこで誰かがへたり込んでらっしゃいますよ?
CHAPTER 006
Sh-Shinobu!
し 忍!
Was it like your body
moved on its own, Araragi-san?
身体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 身体[しんたい, しんだい]:body/physical system/person, 勝手に[かってに]:arbitrarily/of its own accord/voluntarily, 動く[うごく]:to move|to operate|to be touched||, 感じ[かんじ]:feeling/sense/impression
身体が勝手に動いたという感じでしたか? 阿良々木さん
That's strange. Araragi-san, you regretted
saving Shinobu-san over spring break so much.
不思議[ふしぎ]:wonder/miracle/strange, 春休み[はるやすみ]:spring break/spring vacation, 助ける[たすける]:to save|to help|to aid|, あんな:such (about something or someone distant from both speaker and listener, or about a situation unfamiliar to both speaker and listener)/so/that, あんな:Anna or Anwa era (968.8.13-970.3.25), 後悔[こうかい]:regret/repentance/remorse
不思議ですね 阿良々木さんは春休みに忍さんを助けたことを
あんなに後悔してらっしゃったのに
But here, in the same situation,
why did you try to do the same thing again?
同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, シチュエーション:situation, 繰り返す[くりかえす]:to repeat/to do something over again, なさる:to do
どうして同じシチュエーションで
また同じことを繰り返そうとなさったんです?
Well, that's... Um...
えっと:let me see/well/errr ...
それは... その えっと
All I can say is that my body moved on its own.
身体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 身体[しんたい, しんだい]:body/physical system/person, 勝手に[かってに]:arbitrarily/of its own accord/voluntarily, 動く[うごく]:to move|to operate|to be touched||
身体が勝手に動いたとしか...
Well, I still do wonder
あそこ:there (place physically distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|genitals, スルー:ignoring/looking the other way/letting pass, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother
まあ もしも あそこで僕が忍をスルーしていたら
どうなっていたんだろうと
to this day, what would have happened
if I had ignored Shinobu back then.
I think and dream about it even now.
夢[ゆめ]:dream
今でも思うよ 夢に見るよ
Over here!
こっちでーす
Oh, Araragi-san, a pervert
is coming this way. Please be careful.
変態[へんたい]:transformation/metamorphosis|abnormality, 気をつける[きをつける]:to be careful/to pay attention/to take care
おや 阿良々木さん
変態が来ますよ お気をつけて
A pervert is coming? That's a big deal.
変態[へんたい]:transformation/metamorphosis|abnormality, 大変[たいへん]:very|immense|serious||
変態が来る? それは大変なことじゃないか
Hachikuji, hide inside my clothes,
I mean, behind my back.
寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples, 服[ふく]:clothes (esp. Western clothes)|counter for doses of medicine, gulps of tea, drags of a cigarette, etc., 服[ぶく]:mourning clothes|mourning/period of mourning, もとい:(paper) cord for tying the hair, もとい:(in calisthenics) return to your original position!|er, rather (used in speech to correct yourself), 背中[せなか]:back (of body), 隠れる[かくれる]:to hide/to be hidden/to conceal oneself
八九寺 僕の服の中 もとい背中に隠れろ
You've already said "inside my clothes" there.
服[ふく]:clothes (esp. Western clothes)|counter for doses of medicine, gulps of tea, drags of a cigarette, etc., 服[ぶく]:mourning clothes|mourning/period of mourning, 一回[いっかい]:once/one time/one round
服の中って一回言っちゃってますよ
You could say, Araragi-san,
that your life turned tumultuous
助ける[たすける]:to save|to help|to aid|, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death)
忍さんを助けたところから阿良々木さんの人生は
from when you saved Shinobu-san.
波乱[はらん]:disturbance/trouble/ups and downs, 万丈[ばんじょう]:hurrah!/long life/congratulations, 言える[いえる]:to be possible to say/to be able to say
波乱万丈になったと言えますけれど
But if you say that,
a big aspect was you getting to know
助ける[たすける]:to save|to help|to aid|, 直前[ちょくぜん]:just before
それを言うなら 忍さんを助ける直前に
Hanekawa-san right before
you saved Shinobu-san.
知り合う[しりあう]:to get to know (someone)/to make acquaintance, 大きい[おおきい]:big/large/great
羽川さんと知り合ったことも大きいですよね
Well, I won't deny that it was
Hanekawa's fault in all sorts of ways.
色々[いろいろ]:various|various colors (colours), 否定[ひてい]:negation/denial|NOT operation
まあ 色々と羽川のせいだってことは否定しないよ
Because she doesn't know everything, but knows only
what she knows, and exposed truths she didn't need to,
暴く[あばく]:to disclose/to divulge|to open (and rob) a grave, 真実[しんじつ, さな]:truth/reality, 片っ端[かたっぱし]:one edge/one end/one side
なんでもは知らない 知ってることだけのあいつが
暴(あば)かなくてもいい真実を片っ端から暴き
and because she forgot truths
that she didn't have to forget,
忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of, 真実[しんじつ, さな]:truth/reality, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
忘れなくてもいい真実を忘れてしまったがゆえに
we went through reckless shortcuts
and impossible detours this whole time.
達[たち]:pluralizing suffix (esp. for people & animals; formerly honorific), 達[だち, ダチ]:friend, 無茶[むちゃ, むっちゃ]:absurd/unreasonable|very, 近道[ちかみち]:short way/shortcut, 遠回り[とおまわり]:detour/roundabout way
僕達は無茶な近道と
ありえない遠回りをさせられてきたんだから
But...
でも
Even then, I am glad
that I became friends with her.
友達[ともだち]:friend/companion
それでもあいつと友達になってよかったと
That, I believe from the bottom of my heart.
僕は心から思うよ
Senjougahara!
戦場ヶ原...
I believe there was an option here to not catch
Senjougahara-san after her foot slipped.
足[あし]:foot|leg|gait||, 足[そく]:counter for pairs (of socks, shoes, etc.), 滑る[すべる]:to glide|to fail (an examination)|to drop, 滑る[ぬめる, なめる]:to be slippery/to be slimy|to behave charmingly, 受け止める[うけとめる]:to catch/to stop the blow|to react to, 選択[せんたく]:selection/choice/option
ここで足を滑らせた戦場ヶ原さんを
受け止めないという選択も あったと思うんですよね
BACK THEN, SENJOUGAHARA-SAN HAD ALMOST NO WEIGHT
SO SHE PROBABLY WOULD NOT HAVE GOTTEN INJURED
But Araragi-san...
でも 阿良々木さんは
I'll catch her, as many times as I need to,
受け止める[うけとめる]:to catch/to stop the blow|to react to, 何度[なんど]:how many times?/how often?
受け止めるよ 何度でも
if Senjougahara would come falling down.
降る[くだる]:to descend|to be handed down (of an order, judgment, etc.)|to pass (of time)||, 降る[ふる]:to precipitate/to fall (e.g. rain)
戦場ヶ原が降って来たなら
Suppose that, back then,
if you had not caught Senjougahara-san.
仮[け]:lacking substance and existing in name only/something without substance, 仮[かり]:temporary|fictitious|hypothetical, 受け止める[うけとめる]:to catch/to stop the blow|to react to
仮に もしもこのとき
阿良々木さんが戦場ヶ原さんを受け止めていなかったら
That con artist is going to show up
in this town shortly after this, right?
少し[すこし]:small quantity|little while|short distance, 町[まち, ちょう]:town|street|109.09 m||, 詐欺師[さぎし]:swindler/imposter/crook, いらっしゃる:to come/to go|is (doing)
もう少しするとこの町には
あの詐欺師(さぎし)のかたがいらっしゃるんですよね?
The con artist... Deishu Kaiki.
詐欺師[さぎし]:swindler/imposter/crook, 泥舟[どろぶね]:boat to transport mud|(fictional) boat made of (dried) mud
詐欺師... 貝木 泥舟(でいしゅう)
If, back then, you had not gotten
in the way, Araragi-san,
邪魔[じゃま]:hindrance|to visit (somebody's home)|demon who hinders Buddhist training, 立て[たて]:central|just (done)|counter for consecutive losses, 立て[だて]:particularly|indicates the number of horses or oxen drawing a carriage|indicates the number of movies, plays, etc. comprising a single program, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother
もしもあのとき
阿良々木さんが邪魔立てしていなければ
perhaps they may have
gotten back together again?
元鞘[もとさや]:returning to normal after all is said and done
元鞘(もとさや)ってこともあったんじゃないですかね?
How is it, Araragi-san?
どうですか? 阿良々木さん
If you imagined that perhaps you got in the way
of Senjougahara-san and Kaiki-san's romance...
ラブロマンス:love story/romance/love affair, 邪魔[じゃま]:hindrance|to visit (somebody's home)|demon who hinders Buddhist training, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.), しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known, 想像[そうぞう]:imagination/guess
もしも戦場ヶ原さんと貝木さんのラブロマンスを
邪魔してしまったかもしれないと想像すると
If I imagined?
想像[そうぞう]:imagination/guess
想像すると?
All the same, I can't help but think,
"Serves you right!"
さすが:as one would expect|still/all the same, さすが:dagger, 思える[おもえる]:to seem/to appear likely
そんなのはさすがに
ざまあみろとしか思えないよ
It seems she was obliged
to Kaiki concerning Sengoku.
件[くだん]:the aforementioned/the said|the usual, 件[けん]:matter/case/item, 確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken, 世話になる[せわになる]:to receive favor (favour)/to be much obliged to someone/to be indebted
千石の件で 貝木には確かに世話になったようだけれども...
But, that is a completely different matter.
話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
それとこれとは話が別異だ
I can say from the bottom of my heart
that I was better off never meeting him.
言える[いえる]:to be possible to say/to be able to say
あいつとは会わないほうがよかったと
心から言えるぜ
Then lastly, let's walk around the bit
about Sengoku-san, who you just mentioned.
最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments, 挙がる[あがる]:to rise|to enter (esp. from outdoors)|to enter (a school)||, 巡る[めぐる]:to go around|to return|to surround|
では 最後に名前の挙がった千石さんのところを巡りましょうか
Wait, what about Kanbaru?
ん... あれ? 神原は?
That is a different part.
別枠[べつわく]:additional/extraordinary/outside the norms
別枠です
About Shinobu, about Hanekawa,
about Senjougahara, and of course about Hachikuji...
関する[かんする]:to concern/to be related, もちろん:of course/certainly/naturally, 寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples
忍に関しても 羽川に関しても 戦場ヶ原に関しても
もちろん八九寺に関しても
If I were to come across
the same situation again,
何度[なんど]:how many times?/how often?, 同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, シチュエーション:situation, 遭遇[そうぐう]:encounter/being confronted with (e.g. difficulty)/meeting with (e.g. accident)
僕は何度同じシチュエーションに遭遇しても
I'm sure I would do the same thing
over and over again.
何度[なんど]:how many times?/how often?, 同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, 繰り返す[くりかえす]:to repeat/to do something over again
何度だって同じことを繰り返すんだろうけれども
But, no matter what I do, I can't deny
the feeling that I could have done it better.
もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, うまい:skillful/skilful|delicious, 気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|, たって:strongly hoping or requesting (of something that is difficult to be brought to fruition), たって:even if/even though|however, 否定[ひてい]:negation/denial|NOT operation
だけども もっとうまくやれたんじゃないかという気持ちは
どうしたって否定できない
I think you are doing plenty fine,
Araragi-san.
十分[じっぷん, じゅっぷん]:10 minutes, 十分[じゅうぶん]:plenty|division into ten|perfectly, うまい:skillful/skilful|delicious
十分うまくやっていると思いますよ 阿良々木さんは
At least, everything that concerns myself.
少ない[すくない]:few/a little/scarce, わたし:I/me|private affairs, わたし:ferry (crossing)/ferry(boat)|delivery, 関する[かんする]:to concern/to be related
少なくともわたしに関して言うならば
When you say that,
it gives me a small feeling of salvation.
少し[すこし]:small quantity|little while|short distance, 救う[すくう]:to rescue from/to help out of/to save, 気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|
そう言ってくれると
少しは救われた気持ちになるけれどな
But at the least, when we're talking
about Sengoku, I failed.
少ない[すくない]:few/a little/scarce, 関する[かんする]:to concern/to be related, 失敗[しっぱい]:failure/mistake/blunder
だけど少なくとも千石に関して言うなら
僕は失敗した
On the steps of the actual mountain,
when I passed by Nadeko Sengoku...
階段[かいだん]:stairs/stairway/staircase, 撫子[なでしこ, ナデシコ]:pink (any flower of genus Dianthus, esp. the fringed pink, Dianthus superbus)|lovable, caressable girl, すれ違う[すれちがう]:to pass by one another|to miss meeting each other|to disagree
本当のこの山の階段で千石撫子とすれ違ったときには
Back then, I couldn't come to realize
that she was her.
際[きわ, ぎわ]:edge/brink|time, 際[さい]:on the occasion of/circumstances/juncture, 気付く[きづく]:to notice/to recognize/to recognise, ことができる:can (do)/to be able to (do)/can be done
その際には彼女が彼女だと 気付くことができなかった
I don't know about that.
After all, you aren't omnipotent.
万能[ばんのう, まんのう]:all-purpose/utility|almighty
どうでしょうねえ 万能じゃあないんですから
You should distinguish things like that,
like Hanekawa-san.
辺[へん]:area|side|circumstances, 辺[へ, べ]:surrounding area|shore (of the sea)|suffix used as a rough indicator of location, direction, time, etc., 弁える[わきまえる]:to know (right from wrong)/to discern/to discriminate
その辺は弁(わきま)えたほうがいいですよ
羽川さんのように
Come to think, is Ononoki-san doing well?
斧[おの]:axe/hatchet, 元気[げんき]:lively/full of spirit|healthy
そう言えば 斧乃木さんは元気ですか?
Well, she's doing well.
元気[げんき]:lively/full of spirit|healthy
まあ 元気だよ
I see. Then, as the one who assigned her
to be my successor,
後任[こうにん]:successor, 指名[しめい]:name/nominate/designate
そうですか それは彼女を後任に指名した者として
it makes me want to sigh in relief.
胸を撫で下ろす[むねをなでおろす]:to be relieved/to feel relieved, 気分[きぶん]:feeling/mood
胸を撫で下ろしたくなる気分です
Ononoki-chan was your successor?
斧[おの]:axe/hatchet, 乃[の]:possessive particle, 木[き]:tree/shrub|wood, 木[もく]:Thursday|wood (first of the five elements), 後任[こうにん]:successor
斧乃木ちゃん お前の後任だったの?
Yes. The sanctioned successor.
公認[こうにん]:official recognition/authorization/authorisation, 後任[こうにん]:successor
はい 公認の後任です
SANCTIONED (KOUNIN)
SUCCESSOR (KOUNIN)
I'm sure she has delightful chats
unfolding around you, Araragi-san.
きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly, 小気味[こきみ, こきび]:sentiment/feeling, やりとり:giving and taking/exchange (of letters)/arguing back and forth, 繰り広げる[くりひろげる]:to unfold/to unroll/to open
きっと阿良々木さんと
小気味のいいやりとりを繰り広げてらっしゃることでしょう
Come to think, Ononoki-chan isn't included
in this 89-spot pilgrimage, either.
斧[おの]:axe/hatchet, 乃[の]:possessive particle, 木[き]:tree/shrub|wood, 木[もく]:Thursday|wood (first of the five elements), 含む[ふくむ, くくむ]:to contain|to hold in the mouth|to bear in mind|, ヵ所[かしょ]:passage/place/point, 巡り[めぐり]:circumference|tour|circulation (e.g. of blood), 際する[さいする]:to arrive/to come to pass
そう言えば 斧乃木ちゃんも含んでいないんだな
この八十九ヵ所巡りに際しては
WRAP IT UP!
We have time constraints as well.
都合[つごう]:circumstances|to arrange|to lend money|
時間の都合もありますからね
Time constraints?
都合[つごう]:circumstances|to arrange|to lend money|
時間の都合かよ
Yes. Producer Hachikuji
had to make a tough decision.
寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples, 苦渋[くじゅう]:bitterness/mortification/difficulty in understanding, 判断[はんだん]:judgment|divination|judgement
はい 八九寺Pの苦渋(くじゅう)の判断です
Well, the anime shed a lot of light
onto Ononoki-san close up, so it's fine.
斧[おの]:axe/hatchet, アニメ:animated film/animated cartoon/anime (when referring to Japanese cartoons), 結構[けっこう]:splendid|sufficient|well enough||, クローズアップ:close-up
まあ斧乃木さんはアニメで結構クローズアップされたから
いいじゃないですか
You don't have to balance things out
with such a thing.
バランスを取る[バランスをとる]:to keep balance
そんなところでバランスを取られてもな...
Balance.
バランス:balance
バランス
That's what was on my mind.
気になる[きになる]:to be on one's mind|to feel like|to fancy
それが気になっていたのか 僕は
Balance.
バランス:balance
バランス
The right thing.
正しい[ただしい]:right/correct|proper
正しいことを
Yes? What was that, Araragi-san?
はい? なんですか? 阿良々木さん
Well, I was thinking
I had a debate with the Fire Sisters,
正義[せいぎ]:justice/right/righteousness, 標榜[ひょうぼう]:standing for/advocating/championing, ファイヤー:fire
いや いつか正義を標榜(ひょうぼう)するファイヤーシスターズと
an advocate of justice,
about something like that.
議論[ぎろん]:argument/discussion/dispute, ことがある:(something) has occurred/to have done (something)|(something) happens on occasions
そんなような議論をしたことがあったと思ってさ
I suddenly was reminded of it.
不意[ふい]:sudden/abrupt/unexpected, 思い出す[おもいだす]:to recall/to remember/to recollect
不意に思い出しちまった
Well, we're almost at the pinnacle, so if
there's more you want to discuss, keep it short.
山頂[さんちょう]:summit (of a mountain), 話す[はなす]:to talk|to tell|to speak (a language), ことがある:(something) has occurred/to have done (something)|(something) happens on occasions, 手短[てみじか]:short/brief
まあ もうすぐ山頂ですので
話したいことがあるのならば手短に
Because that will most likely be
our final talk session.
たぶん:informing, たぶん:perhaps/probably|generous, わたし:I/me|private affairs, わたし:ferry (crossing)/ferry(boat)|delivery, 最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments, トーク:talk (esp. by a talk-show host, or by a stage musician to the audience between songs)/banter/chat
たぶんそれがわたしとの最後のトークになりますから
What?
THEN, I WANT TO TALK ABOUT SOMETHING ELSE.
It was a talk about how it's difficult
to do the right thing.
正しい[ただしい]:right/correct|proper, 難しい[むずかしい, むつかしい]:difficult|fussy|gloomy||, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
正しいことをするって 難しいよなって話
Most people are eager to correct mistakes
more than doing the right thing, right?
大抵[たいてい]:mostly|probably|most||, 正しい[ただしい]:right/correct|proper, 間違い[まちがい]:mistake|accident|improper conduct (e.g. between man and woman), 正す[ただす]:to correct|to adjust|to ascertain|, 躍起[やっき]:desperation/eagerness
大抵の人は 正しいことをするよりも
間違いを正すことのほうに躍起(やっき)になるだろう?
Doing the right thing
and correcting mistakes are different?
正しい[ただしい]:right/correct|proper, 間違い[まちがい]:mistake|accident|improper conduct (e.g. between man and woman), 正す[ただす]:to correct|to adjust|to ascertain|
正しいことをするのと 間違いを正すことは違いますか?
It's similar but different.
It's not on the mark, but pretty close.
似る[にる]:to resemble/to look like|to be similar (in status, condition, etc.), 非[ひ]:fault|going poorly|un-, 当たる[あたる]:to be hit|to touch|to be equivalent to||, 遠[とお]:distant
似て非なると言うか
当たらずといえども遠からずと言うか
THE ACT OF "CORRECTING A MISTAKE"
MAKES PEOPLE FEEL LIKE
THEY ARE "DOING THE RIGHT THING"—
If you keep correcting mistakes...
間違い[まちがい]:mistake|accident|improper conduct (e.g. between man and woman), 正す[ただす]:to correct|to adjust|to ascertain|, 続ける[つづける]:to continue/to keep up/to keep on
間違いを正し続けていけば
If you crush mistakes one by one,
will it be a pure white kind of right someday?
一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 潰す[つぶす]:to smash|to shut down|to thwart||, 真っ白[まっしろ, ましろ]:pure white|blank (e.g. mind, paper), 正しい[ただしい]:right/correct|proper
ミスを一つずつ潰していけば
いつかはそれは 真っ白な正しさになるんだろうか
If I had to pick, I'd say
it would be a pitch black kind of right.
どちら:which way/which direction|which one (esp. of two alternatives), 真っ黒[まっくろ]:pitch black, 正しい[ただしい]:right/correct|proper
どちらかと言えば真っ黒な正しさになりそうだけど
Anyways, in a nutshell,
that's what I want to know.
ともかく:anyhow/anyway/somehow or other, 煎じ詰める[せんじつめる]:to boil down/to condense
ともかく 煎じ詰めれば
僕が知りたいのはそういうことだ
But, if you go that route,
you won't obtain what you really want.
欲しい[ほしい]:wanted/wished for|I want (you) to, 手に入る[てにはいる]:to obtain/to come into possession of/to get hold of
ただ そのやりかただと
本当に欲しいものは手に入りませんよね
I can't obtain...
手に入る[てにはいる]:to obtain/to come into possession of/to get hold of
手に入らない...
...what I really want?
欲しい[ほしい]:wanted/wished for|I want (you) to
本当に欲しいもの?
Because it's on the premise
that someone else is evaluating.
評価[ひょうか]:valuation|to value|to appreciate, 前提[ぜんてい]:preamble/premise/reason
誰かに評価されることが前提じゃあないですか
At that rate, you'll only receive
what others give you.
もらえる:to be able to receive/to be able to take|could you (give me)
それでは 人がくれるものしかもらえませんよ
Of course, I'm not saying that's a bad thing
もちろん:of course/certainly/naturally, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing, ではある:to be (in contrast to something that is not the case)
もちろん それが悪いというわけではありませんが
If, like you, Araragi-san, one sought something
beyond reach, or something you don't deserve,
みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, 手に余る[てにあまる]:to be beyond one's capacities/to be beyond one's powers/to be beyond one's control, 身に余る[みにあまる]:to be undeserved/to be more than one deserves|to be more than one can handle, 求める[もとめる]:to want|to request|to seek|, 場合[ばあい]:case/situation
阿良々木さんみたいに
手に余るものや身に余るものを求めた場合は
such a method
would prove to be impossible.
無理[むり]:unreasonable|impossible|forcible||
そのやりかたでは無理でしょうね
MAKING MANY MISTAKES
HAVING MANY FAILURES
DOING THINGS OVER
REPEATING THINGS
HESITATING
STAMPING ONE'S FEET IN FRUSTRATION
REPEATING BY TRIAL AND ERROR
AND BEYOND LOUD PROTESTS—
The only thing you can do is succeed, right?
成功[せいこう]:success/hit
成功するしかないんじゃないですか?
It's not like I didn't particularly
want to talk about myself here.
取り立てる[とりたてる]:to collect (debts)|to appoint|to emphasize, 話をする[はなしをする]:to have a talk/to tell a story
別に... 取り立てて僕の話をしたかったわけじゃあないんだけれどな
But well, maybe that is the case.
No, that's how it should be.
でもまあ そうなのかもな
いや そうであるべきなんだろう
You just said you weren't speaking
about yourself.
ご自身[ごじしん]:himself/yourself/herself, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc., なさる:to do, 仰る[おっしゃる]:to say/to speak/to tell
ご自身の話をなさっているのではないと仰いましたね
Then, who were you speaking about?
どなた:who?, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc., なさる:to do
では どなたの話をなさってらっしゃったのですか?
Was it the defenders of justice,
the Fire Sisters?
正義[せいぎ]:justice/right/righteousness, 味方[みかた]:friend/ally/supporter, ファイヤー:fire
正義の味方 ファイヤーシスターズだろうか?
Was it a story about Oshino?
野[の, や]:plain|hidden (structural) member|wild|, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
忍野の話... だったのだろうか?
That's not it.
違うな
Probably, what I wanted to say...
たぶん:informing, たぶん:perhaps/probably|generous
たぶん 今
僕が言いたかったのは
What I wanted to talk about... was her.
話す[はなす]:to talk|to tell|to speak (a language)
話したかったのは
彼女
The transfer student.
転校生[てんこうせい]:transfer student/student changing schools
転校生
Meme Oshino's niece.
野[の, や]:plain|hidden (structural) member|wild|, 姪[めい]:niece
忍野メメの姪
Ougi Oshino. It was about her.
野[の, や]:plain|hidden (structural) member|wild|, 扇[おうぎ, おおぎ]:folding fan
忍野 扇(おうぎ)だ 彼女についてだ
Why didn't her name
cross my mind until right now?
今まで[いままで]:until now/so far/up to the present, 脳裏を過ぎる[のうりをよぎる]:to cross one's mind/to occur to one/to flash into one's head
どうして今まで
その名が脳裏(のうり)を過(よ)ぎらなかったのか
Why couldn't I remember her?
Isn't that a bit strange?
思い出す[おもいだす]:to recall/to remember/to recollect, 不思議[ふしぎ]:wonder/miracle/strange
彼女のことを思い出せなかったのか
不思議じゃあないか
She is the one who, of my past year,
一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||
彼女こそ 僕のこの一年の
was the most important person
in the second half.
後半[こうはん]:second half/latter half, 最重要[さいじゅうよう]:most important, 人物[じんぶつ]:person|one's character|able person
後半における最重要人物だったというのに
Hello, Araragi-kun.
I've been waiting for you.
こんにちは:hello/good day (daytime greeting)
こんにちは 阿良々木くん 待っていたよ